Guide to the UH Frontier Fiesta Collection 1996-003
University of Houston Libraries Special Collections
UH Frontier Fiesta Collection
1941-2014
1952-1959
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
University of Houston
1996-003
5.0 Linear Feet
Paper records related to Frontier Fiesta, dating from 1941 to 2006. Materials have been arranged by series, and chronologically within each. Materials found in this collection include programs, newspaper clippings, financial records, contracts, applications, rules and regulations, show scripts, correspondence, and photographs.
Historical Information
The original Frontier Fiesta was only presented in 1940 and 1941 and conceived by Dr. Kemmerer, who later became president. The monies raised at the first Fiesta, $2,000, contributed to the construction of a campus recreation building. During World War II Frontier Fiesta took a hiatus, but resumed with vigor in 1946. Frontier Fiesta was held in "Fiesta City," which was built each year by students. The buildings each housed different productions. Concessions and contests, including a beard growing contest, were also part of the events.
During its heyday Frontier Fiesta would attract as many as 100,000 people to the UH campus including celebrities and visitors from all over the nation. The 1955 Fiesta signed over a check for $106,000 to help pay for the University's swimming pool. By the early 1950s Frontier Fiesta had been proclaimed as the "Greatest College Show on Earth."
For a variety of reasons, probably including students missing classes and concerns about budget management, Frontier Fiesta was discontinued after 1959. Although briefly replaced in 1961 by Cougar Capers, it would be 33 years before Frontier Fiesta would return to the University of Houston. In 1992 a group of alumni joined an energetic group of student leaders to resurrect the long-gone tradition. This group along with the University of Houston's Athletic Department brought Fiesta back to the campus where it had begun. Frontier Fiesta celebrates everything that makes the University of Houston important to the Houston community today – the talent and leadership ability of its students, the opportunity to educate Houston's future leaders, and scholarship opportunities for deserving students.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Digital archival materials acquired 2014.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research.
Digital Collections
UH Frontier Fiesta Collection digital collection (http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/p15195coll14)
Technical Requirements
Digital archival materials can be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room by advance request. These materials may require up to one week to access. Contact curator Mary Manning (mmmanning@uh.edu) for more information.
Scope and Contents
Paper records related to Frontier Fiesta, dating from 1941 to 2006. Materials have been arranged by series, and chronologically within each. Materials found in this collection include programs, newspaper clippings, financial records, contracts, applications, rules and regulations, show scripts, correspondence, and photographs.
Series 7 contains digital archival materials produced in 2014.
University of Houston
- Programs
  - Programs, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Programs, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Programs, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Programs, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Programs, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Programs, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Programs, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Programs, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Crow's Nest Program, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Programs, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Proofs for Programs, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Programs, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Show Programs, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Programs, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Programs, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Programs, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Programs, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Publications
  - Fiesta Gazette
    - Fiesta Gazette, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Fiesta Gazette, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Fiesta Gazette, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Fiesta Gazette, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Fiesta Gazette, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Fiesta Gazette, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Fiesta Gazette, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Fiesta Gazette, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Fiesta Gazette, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Fiesta Gazette, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Fiesta Gazette, approximately 1960 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Fiesta Gazette, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Fiesta Gazette, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - The Cougar/Daily Cougar
    - The Cougar, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - The Cougar, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - The Cougar, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - The Cougar, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - The Cougar, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Daily Cougar: Nova, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Daily Cougar, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Other UH publications
    - The Extra, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Fiesta City Star, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - The Extra, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - The Extra, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - The Extra, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - The Line, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - UHouston, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Publicity materials
    - Buick Magazine, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Postcards to staff, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Promotional brochure, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Bumper sticker and decal, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Giant Greeting cards, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Dance Fliers, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Proclamation of Frontier Fiesta Week, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Invitation, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Southerner ad for Silver Moon Saloon, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Fliers, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Gulfgate advertising supplement, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Houston Post cartoon ad, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Houston Press ad, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Invitation, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Publicity materials, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Ad, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Frontier Fiesta Currency, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Fiesta City signs and maps (Drawer Z.3, Folder 13)
      - Frontier Fiesta cardboard signs, approximately 1950s (Drawer Z.3, Folder 13, Item 1-4)
      - Frontier Fiesta map, undated (Drawer Z.3, Folder 13, Item 5)
        Immediate Source of Acquisition
        gift of Charles Saunders
      - French Club Cafe drawing, approximately 1940 (Drawer Z.3, Folder 13, Item 6)
- Organizational documents
  - Administrative
    - Resolution forming Frontier Fiesta, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Blueprint for campus, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Organizational paperwork, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Applications for participation, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Parade information, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Schedules and Calendars, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Applications for Participation, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Faculty Questionnaire, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Theme Ideas, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Alumni Participation, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Applications for Participation, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Security regulations and maps, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Committee meetings, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Faculty Questionnaire, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Eligibility Information, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Miscellaneous notes, phone numbers, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Official memorandums, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Prep work for 1958, PR Class comments, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - PR Class reports, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Printing samples, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Proposals and advance work, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Security regulations, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Visible Week calendar, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Emergency services, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Minutes, memos, contests, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Mock-ups, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Organizational charts, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - PR class evaluation, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Parade information, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Participants, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Continuation poll, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Planning paperwork, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - Planning paperwork, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Schedule of events, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 2000s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Financial
    - Financial Paperwork, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Financial Paperwork, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Financial Paperwork, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Financial Paperwork, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Financial Paperwork, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Financial Paperwork, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Financial Paperwork, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Financial Paperwork, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Financial Paperwork, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Account books
    - Account books (2), 1947 (Box 9, Item 1-2)
    - Account book, 1953 (Box 9, Item 3)
    - Account book, 1954 (Box 9, Item 4)
    - Account books (3), 1958 (Box 9, Item 5-7)
    - Bound Programs/Scrapbook, 1940-1957 (Box 9, Item 8)
  - Show production
    - Miscellaneous paperwork, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Booklet of money, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Booklet of money, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Song list, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous paperwork, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Annie Oakley Contest, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Official Rules - Beard Growing Contest, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Stationery, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Booklets of money, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Cast lists, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous paperwork, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Stationery, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Booklets of money, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Miscellaneous paperwork, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Press cards and passes, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Show materials, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Beard contest, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Beard Judge pass, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Booklet of money, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Concession/Food pass, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Dance tickets, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Judging forms, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Miscellaneous paperwork, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Scripts and show materials, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Stationery, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Table tent, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Booklets of money, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Judging/Scoring information, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Scripts, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Miscellaneous paperwork, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Frontier Fiesta song, approximately 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Camera pass, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Houston Fat Stock Show, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Judging forms, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Scripts, costumes, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Materials list, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Script, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Sign, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Bayou Queen script, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Handbooks
    - Handbook, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Publicity booklet, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Handbook with additions, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Handbook, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Handbook, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - The Road to Fiesta City, 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - The Road to Fiesta City, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Road to Fiesta City, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Meeting Minutes
    - Meeting Minutes, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Awards
    - Certificates/Awards, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Certificates/Awards, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Key Awards, information about, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Newspaper clippings
  - Newspaper article, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper clipping, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
  - Dave Parker cartoon, approximately 1960 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Houston Viva article, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Oversized newspaper clipping, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Photographs
  - Photographs, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - Photographs, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - Photographs, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - Photographs, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Photographs, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 4-7)
  - Photographs, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
  - First Beard Contest negatives, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Kick-off Dance negatives, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Negatives, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Negatives, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Photographs, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Life Magazine photographs, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Transcription discs
  - Frontier Fiesta Spots (April 16-21), April 6, 1956 (Box 9, Item 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Side 1 1. :23 Richard Widmark 2. :22 Richard Widmark 3. :23 Bill Roberts 4. :22 Bill Roberts 5. :28 Eddy Arnold 6. :17 Eddy Arnold 7. :11 Eddy Arnold 7A. :25 Oscar Holcombe (same as track 8 on side 2)
    Side 2 8. :25 Oscar Holcombe 9. :28 Oscar Holcombe 10. :26 A. J. Montalbano 11. :23 Buster Kern 12. :22 Buster Kern 13. :24 Paul Hochuli 14. :20 Paul Hochuli 15. :45 Hebert & Wishnow
  - Frontier Fiesta Spots - Western & Popular (2 copies) (Box 9, Item 2-3)
    Side 1 (Western) 1. Jerry Jerico 2. Jack Derrick - Straight 3. Jack Derrick - Comedy 4. Hank Thompson 5. Biff Collie - Straight
    6. Biff Collie - Comedy 7. Background Guitar for Fiesta Pitch
    Side 2 (Popular) 1. Mayor Roy Hofheinz 2. Sheriff Buster Kern 3. Chief Jack Heard 4. Bill Roberts 5. Johnny Desmond 6. Peggy King 7. Ed Sullivan
- Unprocessed electronic materials
  This series contains digital archival materials, which can be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room by advance request. Digital materials include photos from Frontier Fiesta 2014, and interviews of Frontier Fiesta alumni conducted by Student Video Network. These materials may require up to one week to access. Contact University Archivist Mary Manning at mmmanning@uh.edu for more information.